<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>philosophy on Nathan Cheever</title>
    <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/tags/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in philosophy on Nathan Cheever</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.nathancheever.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Life in the Face</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/life_in_the_face/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/life_in_the_face/</guid>
      <description>My first triathlon is now only a few weeks away. Actually it&amp;rsquo;s more of a biathlon for me since my friend Tyler is doing the swimming leg. When he finishes, I&amp;rsquo;ll bike 14 miles and run three. But the constant wind, snow, and rain of this interminable winter have made training outside challenging.
So last Thursday after work I headed over to the gym at my work building. I changed into my running shorts in the bathroom and then entered the gym.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Recommend Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/why_philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/why_philosophy/</guid>
      <description>Mark Twain once said:
&amp;ldquo;Philosophy is fatal to prejudice, bigotry, and narrow-mindedness, and many of our people need it sorely on these accounts. Broad, wholesome, charitable views of men and things cannot be acquired by vegetating in one little corner of the earth all one&amp;rsquo;s lifetime.&amp;rdquo;
Actually, the first word he said was &amp;lsquo;Travel&amp;quot;. Read it again with &amp;ldquo;Travel&amp;rdquo; and you&amp;rsquo;ll see that the two are interchangeable. They&amp;rsquo;re similar in that respect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human Free Will is a Qualitative Reality</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/freewill/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/freewill/</guid>
      <description>A year ago, free will was freedom to do what I wish. Eating a bowl of delicious honey nut cherrios now or later. Wearing the button down shirt I wore yesterday that doesn&amp;rsquo;t smell bad or a fresh one.
Also, to decide who I will be, my attitudes, my priorities. To be the captain of my soul. That fullness of ability I often neglect yet that can still inspire me. That was free will.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can Science Really Answer Moral Questions?</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/can_science_answer_moral_questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/can_science_answer_moral_questions/</guid>
      <description>Sam Harris debunked traditional morality in favor of science in a 2010 TED talk entitled “Science can answer moral questions”.
I disagree with Sam Harris that science can answer moral questions.
But first a small preface. My goal is not to criticize unfairly, but attempt to tackle the core of his argument head on, not sidestep to arguments that, though they may be valid, don’t hit his main points. I also want so say that I am not personally attacking Mr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is that True?</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/relative/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/relative/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s all relative&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ndash; A relative.
Demolition brings a draft Five years ago, I decided it was time for spiritual and intellectual remodeling. I was more excited for the demolition than the rebuilding. My faiths and philosophies were flimsy and distorted. And they needed to go. So I picked up my proverbial wrecking bar and went to town. It was my life and I was determined to search for truth on my own.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
