<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>philosophy on Nathan Cheever</title>
    <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/tags/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in philosophy on Nathan Cheever</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.nathancheever.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>If a thing is worth doing</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/if_a_things_worth_doing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/if_a_things_worth_doing/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;rsquo;s the old saying, &amp;ldquo;If a thing is worth doing, it&amp;rsquo;s worth doing well.&amp;rdquo; I, like many of you, was raised on this saying and others like it. &amp;ldquo;If you&amp;rsquo;re going to do a job, do it right the first time.&amp;rdquo; That was another of my mom&amp;rsquo;s favorites. These sayings are aiming at doing good work rather than sloppy careless efforts.
If I&amp;rsquo;m going to clean the kitchen, do a good job wiping off the counters, getting the toast crumbs under the toaster, and cleaning out the sink.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The philosophy of the newspaper</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/philosophy_of_news/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/philosophy_of_news/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Philosophy and &amp;hellip;newspapers!? What could these two totally unrelated things possibly have in common except being antiquated and therefore something I&amp;rsquo;m bound to be interested in? Well, in this post I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you what I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered after weeks of intense research about the newspaper: the industry, the product, and the why behind it all (that&amp;rsquo;s where the philosophy comes in!). If you stick around till the end, I&amp;rsquo;ll layout what I think are the keys to using philosophy and some modern adaptations to revitalize the newspaper industry, and perhaps a sense of local community with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s up with Up?</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/whats_up_with_up/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/whats_up_with_up/</guid>
      <description>The meaning of lines A horizontal line is sensed as &amp;ldquo;being at rest, just as the human body is at rest when horizontal. They give a sense of stability, balance, and tranquility.&amp;rdquo;1
A vertical line is sensed as &amp;ldquo;one of aspiration, reaching, assertiveness&amp;rdquo;2. Instead of the restful equilibrium you see with horizontal lines, we get a dynamic equilibrium. There are forces held in check, just like a human body standing takes lots of muscles to keep it upright, or the strength of a tree&amp;rsquo;s roots holding the tree against the wind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Love, cheese, and dead French philosophers</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/to_know_to_love/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/to_know_to_love/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve picked up reading Blaise Pascal&amp;rsquo;s Pensées lately and this statement made me wonder:
&amp;ldquo;The greater the intellect one has, the more originality one finds in men. Ordinary persons find no difference between men.&amp;rdquo;1
Do you agree?
Intelligence corresponds with an ability to see, perceive, and find things. And not just regular objects, but qualities such as uniqueness, originality, and worth. Failing to see difference in men could mean one is more prone to prejudice and bias.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Essential Philamping Packing List</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/philamping/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/philamping/</guid>
      <description>Today I want to talk to you about philamping and what to pack for it so you&amp;rsquo;re prepared. &amp;ldquo;Phila-what?&amp;rdquo;, I hear you asking. Yes, I made that word up. I guess that&amp;rsquo;s the kind of thing that happens when you&amp;rsquo;re driving across the country in a Uhaul with no radio or smartphone. My mind starts to mash up words. It means philosophical camping. I don&amp;rsquo;t think this term exists, but it ought to, as I&amp;rsquo;ll explain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Recommend Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/why_philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/why_philosophy/</guid>
      <description>Mark Twain once said:
&amp;ldquo;Philosophy is fatal to prejudice, bigotry, and narrow-mindedness, and many of our people need it sorely on these accounts. Broad, wholesome, charitable views of men and things cannot be acquired by vegetating in one little corner of the earth all one&amp;rsquo;s lifetime.&amp;rdquo;
Actually, the first word he said was &amp;lsquo;Travel&amp;quot;. Read it again with &amp;ldquo;Travel&amp;rdquo; and you&amp;rsquo;ll see that the two are interchangeable. They&amp;rsquo;re similar in that respect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human Free Will is a Qualitative Reality</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/freewill/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/freewill/</guid>
      <description>A year ago, free will was freedom to do what I wish. Eating a bowl of delicious honey nut cherrios now or later. Wearing the button down shirt I wore yesterday that doesn&amp;rsquo;t smell bad or a fresh one.
Also, to decide who I will be, my attitudes, my priorities. To be the captain of my soul. That fullness of ability I often neglect yet that can still inspire me. That was free will.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can Science Really Answer Moral Questions?</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/can_science_answer_moral_questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/can_science_answer_moral_questions/</guid>
      <description>Sam Harris debunked traditional morality in favor of science in a 2010 TED talk entitled “Science can answer moral questions”.
I disagree with Sam Harris that science can answer moral questions.
But first a small preface. My goal is not to criticize unfairly, but attempt to tackle the core of his argument head on, not sidestep to arguments that, though they may be valid, don’t hit his main points. I also want so say that I am not personally attacking Mr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is that True?</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/relative/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/relative/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s all relative&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ndash; A relative.
Demolition brings a draft Five years ago, I decided it was time for spiritual and intellectual remodeling. I was more excited for the demolition than the rebuilding. My faiths and philosophies were flimsy and distorted. And they needed to go. So I picked up my proverbial wrecking bar and went to town. It was my life and I was determined to search for truth on my own.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
