<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>philosophy on Nathan Cheever</title>
    <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/tags/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in philosophy on Nathan Cheever</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.nathancheever.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reading the Classics is Good for your Health</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/classics_are_good_for_your_health/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/classics_are_good_for_your_health/</guid>
      <description>Reading the classics of the western world might make you healthier, live longer, and happier. The great books are an equal opportunity boon. You can get them over-the-counter at any bookstore, and take at least once daily until you die.
How? This came to me while I was reading some of Plato&amp;rsquo;s dialogues, the Protagoras and the Gorgias. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a randomized trial with a p-value less than five percent showing me this, but there are other strong reasons to believe in the prescription of good reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can Science Really Answer Moral Questions?</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/can_science_answer_moral_questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/can_science_answer_moral_questions/</guid>
      <description>Sam Harris debunked traditional morality in favor of science in a 2010 TED talk entitled “Science can answer moral questions”.
I disagree with Sam Harris that science can answer moral questions.
But first a small preface. My goal is not to criticize unfairly, but attempt to tackle the core of his argument head on, not sidestep to arguments that, though they may be valid, don’t hit his main points. I also want so say that I am not personally attacking Mr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is that True?</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/relative/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/relative/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s all relative&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ndash; A relative.
 Demolition brings a draft Five years ago, I decided it was time for spiritual and intellectual remodeling. I was more excited for the demolition than the rebuilding. My faiths and philosophies were flimsy and distorted. And they needed to go. So I picked up my proverbial wrecking bar and went to town. It was my life and I was determined to search for truth on my own.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
