<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pieces on Nathan Cheever</title>
    <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pieces on Nathan Cheever</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.nathancheever.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>DeadTED #1: God Is Dead</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/dt1_nietzsche/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/dt1_nietzsche/</guid>
      <description>NOTES FOR THE READER:
I’ve tried to imagine him on a stage and added cues for how I imagine him saying things, pausing at times, etc. As I’ve pulled together fragments across his book “The Gay Science”, sometimes I abbreviate with ‘&amp;hellip;’. These are not to be read as a dramatic pause, but more to indicate that I’ve skipped some of his words. I’ve tried to keep Nietzsche’s italicization&amp;rsquo;s. My words/edits I’ve tried to keep to a minimum and they are indicated in blue (coming soon).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Recommend Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/why_philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/why_philosophy/</guid>
      <description>Mark Twain once said:
&amp;ldquo;Philosophy is fatal to prejudice, bigotry, and narrow-mindedness, and many of our people need it sorely on these accounts. Broad, wholesome, charitable views of men and things cannot be acquired by vegetating in one little corner of the earth all one&amp;rsquo;s lifetime.&amp;rdquo;
Actually, the first word he said was &amp;lsquo;Travel&amp;quot;. Read it again with &amp;ldquo;Travel&amp;rdquo; and you&amp;rsquo;ll see that the two are interchangeable. They&amp;rsquo;re similar in that respect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human Free Will is a Qualitative Reality</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/freewill/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/freewill/</guid>
      <description>A year ago, free will was freedom to do what I wish. Eating a bowl of delicious honey nut cherrios now or later. Wearing the button down shirt I wore yesterday that doesn&amp;rsquo;t smell bad or a fresh one.
Also, to decide who I will be, my attitudes, my priorities. To be the captain of my soul. That fullness of ability I often neglect yet that can still inspire me. That was free will.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compulsion Without a Core</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/political_correctness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/political_correctness/</guid>
      <description>“Peace cannot be kept by force; it can only be achieved by understanding.”1
The Allure of Correctness My senior year of high school I fell perhaps too much in love with English. I gained a bit of a reputation as a grammar Nazi. I took a sort of pleasure in catching people when they dangled prepositions, failed on their subject-verb agreements, and said who when they should have said whom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brooks, Connors, Emerson, and Tolstoy on How to Balance Commitment with Change</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/commit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/commit/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s useful to call up a meeting with your personal board of directors when faced with difficult decisions. In this article, I&amp;rsquo;ll call in a few of mine to see what I can learn about the interplay of commitment and flexibility.
Tolstoy&amp;rsquo;s Young Man with a Big Problem Nikolai Rostov was a young man with a major dilemma. He was betrothed to his cousin Sonya but he wasn&amp;rsquo;t in love with her.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How The Mental Models of Orienteering and Topographic Thinking Can Help Us Understand The World</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/mental_models_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/mental_models_1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Recently, I picked up an old college textbook I&amp;rsquo;d saved, thinking someday I&amp;rsquo;d peruse its pages and maybe get interested in Biology again. Well, the other day I finally did. While reading the introduction, two mental models stood out to me: the mental models of Orienteering and Topographic Thinking.
In this piece, I&amp;rsquo;m going to relate these two models as my professor taught them, and then perhaps in later posts extend it to other concepts and writers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t be upgraded</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/appropriation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/appropriation/</guid>
      <description>Technology offers an interesting set of verbs almost daily: &amp;ldquo;Upgrade&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Sign in&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Create Account&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Buy&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Activate&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Download&amp;rdquo; to name a few off the top of my head. There is always another version. Always more features, fixes and stuff on the digital horizon. We&amp;rsquo;re supposed to be excited, as with the release of a new OS by &amp;ldquo;New experiences. True Connections&amp;rdquo;. Sounds fascinating. And if such upgrades aren&amp;rsquo;t imposed upon us, as sometimes they are, we&amp;rsquo;re invited to be excited&amp;hellip; now and always.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can Science Really Answer Moral Questions?</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/can_science_answer_moral_questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/can_science_answer_moral_questions/</guid>
      <description>Sam Harris debunked traditional morality in favor of science in a 2010 TED talk entitled “Science can answer moral questions”.
I disagree with Sam Harris that science can answer moral questions.
But first a small preface. My goal is not to criticize unfairly, but attempt to tackle the core of his argument head on, not sidestep to arguments that, though they may be valid, don’t hit his main points. I also want so say that I am not personally attacking Mr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is that True?</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/relative/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/relative/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s all relative&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ndash; A relative.
Demolition brings a draft Five years ago, I decided it was time for spiritual and intellectual remodeling. I was more excited for the demolition than the rebuilding. My faiths and philosophies were flimsy and distorted. And they needed to go. So I picked up my proverbial wrecking bar and went to town. It was my life and I was determined to search for truth on my own.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to get up and running with an analog Zettlekästen (slipbox)</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/zettlekasten/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/zettlekasten/</guid>
      <description>Preface There is a veritable plethora of videos and articles on how to setup a digital Zettlekästen. There are tons of blogs and forums about Niklas Luhmann&amp;rsquo;s practice, his prolific publishing record.
So why add another one? Frankly most of them aren&amp;rsquo;t that helpful. I learn by seeing how something is actually done, especially an analog process. And more importantly, I want it to be true to the process Luhmann discovered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Questions to be lived</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/questions/</guid>
      <description>Not often, but sometimes, you stumble upon a question that is so profound to you that you would almost be sad to find the answer. It keeps you searching yourself, calling upon something deeper than rote learning or textbook memorization.
Perhaps we can call these “floating questions.” They evade scientific explanation.
Floating questions demand an answer from your life. They can generate enormous passion, send humans into space, and create beautiful art.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Have a good day, 
Have a good life</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/goodday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/goodday/</guid>
      <description>One golden afternoon last October, while taking a walk, I wrote a thought down: &amp;ldquo;Eventually, my life will just be as good as my days. So I need to enjoy my days if I am going to enjoy my life.&amp;rdquo;
Embedded in there is the idea that no one state or achievement will likely &amp;ldquo;make&amp;rdquo; my life. Instead of some grandiose event, life&amp;rsquo;s quality is subject to more prosaic influences like the quality of our relationships, sleep, self-talk, hobbies, and food.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Please consider rebelling</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/rebel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/rebel/</guid>
      <description>There is a terrible temptation (I know I’ve fallen into many times) to value yourself by your productivity.
The meritocracy culture says monetary accumulation is the gateway to everything we desire: respect, independence, even happiness.
Hearing rhetoric like: “with the internet, not being a millionaire is a choice” for people like me who’ve accomplished very little according to the rules of the game, it can feel absolutely crushing.
Being ordinary is shamed as not hustling hard enough.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/deadteds/ideas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/deadteds/ideas/</guid>
      <description>Sophocles&amp;rsquo; oedipus Randolph Bourne Friedrich Nietzsche from &amp;ldquo;The Gay Science&amp;rdquo; Victor Hugo Dorothy Sayers The Lost Tools of Learning Mircea Eliade The Myth of the Eternal Return</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/deadteds/nietzschesthegayscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/deadteds/nietzschesthegayscience/</guid>
      <description>God Is Dead, Friedrich Nietzsche December 1882, Sils-Maria SWITZERLAND [Nietzsche enters stage right, walks to the center of the stage and stops. He pulls out his glasses]
To find everything deep is an inconvenient quality: it makes us more constantly strain our eyes, [puts on his glasses] and in the end we always find more than we wish.
[light laughter in the crowd N. now, gravely, then quizzically:]
Have you not heard of that madman who lit a lantern in the bright morning light, ran to the marketplace and shouted incessantly, &amp;lsquo;I seek God!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/newsletter/scratch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/newsletter/scratch/</guid>
      <description>Respect. When someone says, &amp;ldquo;I ask that you respect my preferences/choice/decision/identity&amp;rdquo;, how are we to respond? Or perhaps more pointedly: &amp;ldquo;why won&amp;rsquo;t you respect my ?&amp;rdquo;. Perhaps the supposition is, if it&amp;rsquo;s someone&amp;rsquo;s choice, it ought to be respected, observed. But what does respect in this case mean? Is it an invitation or an injunction to show admiration and deference to something worthy of those feelings? OED: to treat or regard with deference, esteem, or honor; to feel or show respect for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/0-preface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/0-preface/</guid>
      <description>Ball or Block? Any discussion of shape and meaning presents a daunting task, especially for the non-expert. My intention is not to elaborate basic geometry, talking about solids, planes, and the different types of shapes. Yet familiarity with shapes is needed. The intuition of why we use spheres for sports instead of using squares is at the same time obvious and illuminating. Even if both objects, the sphere and the square, are made by the same person, with the same material, the same color, if every physical and aesthetic property of them were identical in all respects, the sphere is unquestioningly preferred for sports.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/1-meditations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/1-meditations/</guid>
      <description>Meditations on Shape Everything you see and touch has a shape. It&amp;rsquo;s an elemental property of reality. Shape is an essential to what a thing is. Shape exists as an essence, both in the mind and in the physical world.
Shape is a powerful tool for understanding the world, from biology to chemistry to philosophy. Thinking in shapes will inform your mind and give you clarity.
To be informed is to be shaped by an idea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/2-order/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/2-order/</guid>
      <description>Order I have talked about the potential of thinking in shapes. Now I ask, what makes a shape?
Let&amp;rsquo;s consider the triangle. The triangle can only have three angles and three sides, though those angles and lengths may change, but it cannot simultaneously be a square or a circle. It cannot also be anything or nothing. I have defined a shape as a definite thing. It cannot violate the law of non-contradiction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/3a-boundaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/3a-boundaries/</guid>
      <description>What is the shape of a good life? [[1112/3/1/0]] Socrates is trying to persuade Callicles to &amp;ldquo;choose an ordinary life, the life that is adequate to and satisfied with its circumstances at any given time instead of the insatiable, undisciplined life.&amp;rdquo;1
This runs against the grain of society appetites for immediate gratification, next-day delivery, and unlimited perks. Socrates admonition to Callicles is loaded with the language of limitation. Words like &amp;lsquo;ordinary&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;adequate&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;satisfied with its circumstances&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;insatiable&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;undisciplined&amp;rsquo;, while each has diverse roots, meanings, and can be used in various context, all share an idea of form, of limits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/3b-character/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/3b-character/</guid>
      <description>Character The word &amp;ldquo;character&amp;rdquo; can mean different things in different contexts. In one, it might be an actor on a stage playing a part. In another, a character might refer to a marking, a letter or symbol that carries linguistic or even artistic weight. In common parlance it refers to how someone is known. [[1112/3/-1/2]] David Brooks, in his book The Road to Character defines it as:
&amp;ldquo;as a set of dispositions, desires, and habits that are slowly engraved during a struggle against your own weakness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/4-conformity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/4-conformity/</guid>
      <description>Conformity The word conformity points to forming one&amp;rsquo;s self to something else. It is to comply to an external standard, character or order. It is to be molded into a different shape. Changing order changes the pattern. That alters the meaning that can be gotten from it, and hence the character.
[[1112/4C]] Ralph Waldo Emerson wrote about conformity in a famous essay written in _ entitled Self Reliance. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t had the pleasure, take some time and read through it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/7-telos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/7-telos/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Whether it be the sweeping eagle in his flight, or the open apple-blossom, the toiling work-horse, the blithe swan, the branching oak, the winding stream at its base, the drifting clouds, over all the coursing sun, form ever follows function, and this is the law. Where function does not change, form does not change. The granite rocks, the ever-brooding hills, remain for ages; the lightning lives, comes into shape, and dies, in a twinkling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/the_boundless/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/the_boundless/</guid>
      <description>The Boundless What happens when we go beyond shape to the shapeless? To the boundless, the infinite? To the void? How does our thinking work there? Is it of any use?
Order requires limits. It could be that the quanta or things that create the order are limited, either in limited quanta creating a pattern,
Water has an order. It&amp;rsquo;s based on limited number of things, i.e. Hydrogen and Oxygen. These are the quanta that can be made into water, but not necessarily.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/z_afterword/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/shapes/z_afterword/</guid>
      <description>Afterword This book has been a joint-exploration. I didn&amp;rsquo;t always know where it was going to go, but there seemed to be a truth worth pursuing and discussing. The language and thinking of shapes is so ubiquitous that I needed and wanted to look into what might connect it. How does it hang together and make sense?
If there were a few takeaways for me on this journey they would be:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/tenthinkers/0-nitroduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/tenthinkers/0-nitroduction/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Five years ago, I decided it was time for spiritual and intellectual remodeling. I was more excited for the demolition than the rebuilding. My faiths and philosophies were flimsy and distorted. And they needed to go. It was my life and I was determined to search for truth on my own.
You see I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what I could trust. I felt deeply betrayed by my church and even my faith.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/tenthinkers/1-emerson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/tenthinkers/1-emerson/</guid>
      <description>Ralph Waldo Emerson &amp;ldquo;Whoso would be a man must be a nonconformist. He who would gather immortal palms must not be hindered by the name of goodness, but must explore if it be goodness.&amp;rdquo;
One day in early sprnig I decided to go on a hike. The hike began at my doorstep and I planned to walk across the valley due east until III got into the mountaints. From there I wuold explore and sese what I coudl find.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moderation in moderation</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/moderation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/moderation/</guid>
      <description>There are special times in life to go all out.
Last year, I went all out on a 50-mile hike alone, completing it in 19 hours.
I learned some invaluable lessons like
Don&amp;rsquo;t trust Google maps over mountains (I got lost) Always pack an extra almond poppyseed muffin. Stopping to rest only makes your legs hurt more. More importantly, I learned that after being alone and exhausted for hours, all the noise in your head quiets down, and you come to know yourself and your limits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plato, the moral revolutionary</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/plato/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/plato/</guid>
      <description>Almost 2400 years ago, one of the greatest revolutions the western world has ever known set off.
It was a relatively quiet explosion, not a famous battle or the overthrow of an empire. It was a young man watching his hero, teacher, and mentor put on trial and condemned to death. His teacher had dedicated his life to questioning others, for, as he put it, &amp;ldquo;the unexamined life is not worth living.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small Talk as an Onramp</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/talk/</guid>
      <description>As an introvert, small talk has never come easy for me. I enjoy watching the occasional football or basketball game. Still, I can&amp;rsquo;t talk at length about the recent trades or injuries.
And the latest on TV or streaming shows? Nope, I&amp;rsquo;m lost. I don&amp;rsquo;t say this to boast, for if anything, it&amp;rsquo;s hindered me in quickly finding common ground in the break room.
Last year, I caught a ride home with a coworker who lived nearby.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Relationist</title>
      <link>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/relationist/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nathancheever.com/post/relationist/</guid>
      <description>Last October I was walking to lunch with a friend. The Vice-Presidential debate happened the night before, and I glibly remarked about my hopes for the election outcome. Until that moment, I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize that my friend felt differently.
After about 30 minutes of awkward but polite conversation, it was clear that we disagreed. I tried to mute my sarcasm, but it slipped out once when I said, &amp;ldquo;If Darth Vader pretended to support the policies you supported, would you still vote for him?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
